(612) 814-7892 Minneapolis, Minnesota sivrmn@umn.edu

# Sivaraman Rajaganapathy

sivrmn.github.io/ Ph.D. Candidate, University of Minnesota-Twin Cities linkedin.com/in/sivrmn

A <u>control</u> engineer with experience in <u>machine learning</u> and <u>data analysis</u> for biophysics & biomedical systems and 2 years of industry experience looking forward to contributing to research projects.

#### **EDUCATION**

Ph.D. in Electrical Engineering with Computer Science Minor

Dec 2022 (Expected)

University of Minnesota, Twin-Cities

GPA: 3.789/4

Advisor: Murti Salapaka

Master of Technology in Systems and Control

2013

Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay

GPA: 9.82/10 Advisor: Paluri S V Nataraj

13 v Nataraj

**Bachelor of Engineering in Electrical Engineering** 

2011

University of Mumbai

GPA: 79.04/100

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

## **Performance Improvement of Non-equilibrium Experiments**

JUN 2020 — PRESENT

Ph.D. Project

- Developed algorithm for quantifying errors in non-equilibrium experiments [Presented in APS 2022]
- Released Python based toolbox for error quantification and validated on Optical Tweezers

## **Modeling Nano-Mechanics of Muscle Proteins**

JAN 2017 — PRESENT

Ph.D. Project

- Collaborated with biochemists to design force spectroscopy experiments characterizing single molecules of proteins linked to muscular dystrophy [Published in Nature Scientific Reports 2019]
- Implemented robust force control in an atomic force microscope [Presented in ISPM 2018]
- Developed Monte Carlo methods to capture molecules' observed behaviors
- Devised statistical tests to evaluate proteins for potential therapy
- Conducted experiments revealing effect of expression system on proteins [Presented in BPS 2020]
- Automated experimental analysis, reducing processing time from 1 work day to 2 hours

## **Change Detection Algorithm**

JUL 2016 — JUL 2020

Ph.D. Project

- Constructed a python-based toolbox for detecting abrupt jumps in system parameters under low signal to noise ratios using dynamic programming [Published in Automatica 2022]
- · Explained the behavior of a popular change detection algorithm and found its limits of performance

#### Intelligent Identifier & Auto-Tuner

JUL 2012 — JUN 2013

Received Institute Silver Medal - Master's Thesis

- Developed an expert system to start controlling a plant with limited human supervision from a cold start
- Created algorithm that found models with >60% fit for a large class of systems
- High performance controllers validated on hybrid tank, thermal & motor control systems

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Research Intern

JUN 2021 — AUG 2021

Rhythm Management, Boston Scientific Inc.

Arden Hills, MN

- Deep Learning Performance Analysis: Identified limitations in the training dataset that lead to the prediction errors
- Data Augmentation: Created methods to augment limited training data for improved machine learning model performance

Research Intern

JUN 2019 — AUG 2019

Rhythm Management, Boston Scientific Inc.

Arden Hills, MN

- Rhythm Classification: Developed deep learning models to classify electrocardiograms from implantable devices
- Deep Learning Automation: Built framework for hyper-parameter search (model optimization) and for using unlabeled data

## **Systems Validation Engineer**

**SEPT 2013 — JUN 2015** 

Cypress Semiconductor Corporation

Bengaluru, India

- **Generic Automation Platform:** Developed a generic test system which can be used for automated validation of all Programmable Systems on Chips (PSoC)
- Validation: Designed tests for functional validation of CAN and CapSense blocks and performed preliminary EMI/EMC certification of PSoCs

SEPTEMBER 20, 2022 SIVARAMAN RAJAGANAPATHY 1 OF 2

Applications Engineer JUN 2013 — SEPT 2013

Cypress Semiconductor Corporation

Bengaluru, India

• CapSense Algorithm Development: Developed firmware algorithms for auto-tuning capacitive touch sensors and gesture detection using 4 sensors

Intern JUL 2010 — APR 2011

Siemens Limited (Part Time)

Mumbai, India

- · Built a corona detector for finding electrical discharges in air to aid quality testing of transformers
- Diagnosed & reduced noise problems to achieve a detection range of 40m in air

#### **PROJECTS**

# Deep Reinforcement Learning for Multi-Agent Interaction

SEPT 2017 — DEC 2017

- Investigated conditions that promote agent-agent language evolution from scratch
- Measured performance improvements for bridge crossing when using agent derived communication

## **Robustness of Control Via Deep Reinforcement Learning**

JAN 2017 - MAY 2017

- Evaluated the robustness of control obtained via reinforcement learning
- Improved stability of derived controllers, validated on openAI Gym's unstable cart-pole system

# **Automating Deep Learning for Game Playing**

**SEPT 2016 — DEC 2016** 

- · Created an unsupervised agent that learned to play the game Super Hexagon using only video data
- · Reinforcement learning used to train a neural network to achieve survival times 3x random actions

## **Conveyor Belt Tracking for on the Fly Machine Operations**

FEB 2012 — MAY 2012

• Developed digital PID controllers to enable machine tools to operate on moving objects, with the aim to reduce production time and energy wastage in assembly lines

## Modeling & Control of Vehicle with Four Wheel Steering

JAN 2012 — APR 2012

- · Estimated dynamic models (ARX, ARMAX) for vehicle dynamics from input-output data
- Designed and simulated optimal pole placement controllers with Kalman filters for improved performance and safe operation

#### **SKILLS**

**Technical Python**, **MATLAB**, Simulink, Labview, C, C++, R

Knowledge Base Machine Learning, Artificial Intelligence, Optimization, Filtering, Estimation, Identification

### POSITIONS OF RESPONSIBILITY

Teaching Assistant SEPT 2016 — PRESENT

University of Minnesota, Twin-Cities

- Mentored students on practical control application
- Consistently rate > 5 out of 6 in student feedback
- Upgraded aging hardware and manuals for 2 labs
- Awarded college level John Bowers Excellence Award (2020)

Lab Safety Officer SEPT 2018 — PRESENT

Salapaka Lab | University of Minnesota, Twin-Cities

Graduate Student Mentor MAR 2022 — PRESENT

Electrical and Computer Engineering | University of Minnesota, Twin-Cities

Grants Review Committee MAR 2021 — AUG 2022

Council of Graduate Students | University of Minnesota, Twin-Cities

Alumni Student Mentor MAY 2018 — MAY 2020

Alumni Association | IIT Bombay

Department Placement Coordinator JUL 2012 — MAY 2013

Career Cell | IIT Bombay

Chair JUL 2012 — MAY 2013

IEEE Students' Chapter | Fr. C.R.I.T, University of Mumbai